Guide to the Richard Powell Papers, 1960-2011 RL.01043
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Articles and Lectures by Powell, 1975-2011, 5 boxes
  - "'In my Family of Primitiveness and Tradition' William H. Johnson's Jesus and the Three Marys" (Box 45)
  - "What Becomes a Legend Most?: Reflections on Romare Bearden" (Box 45)
  - "Art, History, and Vision" (Box 45)
  - "Artist and Community: Willie Birch-From Bertrandville to Brooklyn" (Box 45)
  - "Two Paintings by William H. Johnson" (Box 45)
  - "Talking with James Lesesne Wells" (Box 45)
  - "Trouble in the Ebony Tower" (Box 45)
  - "Winslow Homer, Afro-Americans, and the 'New Order of Things'" (Box 45)
  - "Current Expressions in Afro-American Printmaking" (Box 45)
  - Powell MA Thesis (Box 45)
  - "William H. Johnson and the Harmon Foundation: A Study in Afro-American Art Patronage" (Box 45)
  - "Black Folk Art in America, 1930-1980" (Box 45)
  - "The Art of Raymond Saunders: Colored" (Box 45)
  - "William H. Johnson's Minde Kerteminde" (Box 45)
  - "Margo Humphrey Interview" (Box 45)
  - "From the Potomac to the Anacostia" (Box 45)
  - "Shades of Grey in the Black Aesthetic" (Box 45)
  - "African Art at the Field Museum" (Box 45)
  - "On Printmaking" (Box 45)
  - "On Phillis Wheatley" (Box 45)
  - Powell Early Drafts (Box 45)
  - "Phoenix Ascending: The Art of James Lesesne Wells" (Box 46)
  - "From Renaissance to Realization: 1920-50" (Box 46)
  - "The Blues Aesthetic: Black Culture and Modernism" (Box 46)
  - "Cinque: Antislavery Portraiture & Patronage in Jacksonian America" (Box 46)
  - "Anasi Revisited: Keith Morrison's New Work" (Box 46)
  - "The Woodshed in Romare Bearden, American Modernist" (Box 46)
  - "Lenox's Theorem for Right Triangles (Morehouse College)" (Box 46)
  - "MFA Thesis, Howard University" (Box 46)
  - "Elizabeth Catlett and 'the Negro Woman': 1946-47" (Box 46)
  - "Richard Wright" (Box 47)
  - "Re/Birth of a Nation" (Box 47)
  - "Chi-Wara" (Box 47)
  - Rockefeller Foundation Fellowship Final Report (Box 47)
  - Powell PhD Dissertation: "William H. Johnson-Expressionist and Artist of the Blues Aesthetic, Vol. II-Images" (Box 47)
  - "An Examination of Winslow Homer's The Carnival" (Box 47)
    Paper
  - "Surfaces: Andre, Segal, Serra, Smyth, Stuart" (Box 47)
  - "An Examination of Thomas Eakin's Whistling for Plover" (Box 47)
  - "Art History and Black Memory: Toward a 'Blues Aesthetic'" (Box 47)
  - "The Afro-American Printmaking Tradition" (Box 47)
  - "Through Myriad Eyes" (Box 47)
  - "The Art of Bruce Onobrakpeya" (Box 47)
  - "Power Symbols and the Aesthetic Ideal in Harlem Renaissance Representations of Black Women" (Box 47)
  - "Images and Identities: A Brief Introductory Note" (Box 48)
  - "Artist/Scholar Richard J. Powell Interview" (Box 48)
  - "Impressions: Expressions-Black American Graphics" (Box 48)
  - "On Kerry James Marshall" (Box 48)
    Lecture
  - "The Woodshed" (Box 48)
  - "Hendricks Redux" (Box 48)
  - "The Promise of the War Years, 1940-46" (Box 48)
  - "Memory, Representations, and the Black '60s" (Box 48)
  - "Beauties Revisited" (Box 48)
  - "Art Views at Crystal Bridges Museum of American Art" (Box 48)
  - "Art History and Black Memory: Toward a 'Blues Aesthetic'" (Box 48)
  - "Testifying from the Margins: David Gilmour Blythe's Justice" (Box 48)
  - "A Lynching, a Riot, and Bearing Witness: Two Paintings by William H. Johnson" (Box 48)
  - "The Impact of Studies of Afro-American Art and Culture" (Box 48)
  - "Jacob Lawrence" (Box 48)
  - "Musicians at an Exhibition: Miles and Marvin" (Box 48)
  - "Brown Narcissus" (Box 48)
  - "Exploitation/Exultation: a 20th c. Affair" (Box 48)
  - "Ethiopia Awakened, Harlem Sublimated: Aaron Douglas's Call to Modernism" (Box 48)
  - "Sojourner Truth and the Invention of Genteel Domesticity in her Photographic 'Self-Portraiture'" (Box 48)
  - "Cutting a Figure: Fashioning Black Portraiture" (Box 48)
  - "Bronzeville: A Work in Progress" (Box 48)
  - "Sartor Africanus" (Box 48)
  - "Luna Obscura" (Box 48)
  - "The Countenance and Complexion of Freedom" (Box 48)
  - "The Visual Arts and Afro-America, 1940-1980" (Box 48)
  - "Soulsville" (Box 49)
  - "Minstrelsy 'Uncorked': Thomas Eakins Emphatic Realism" (Box 49)
  - "The Promise of the War Years, 1940-46" (Box 49)
  - "Enter and Exit the 'New Negro'" (Box 49)
- Photographs, 1975-2011, 1 box
  This series contains photographs of Powell. Contents include two folders of photographs from Powell's professional career, including gallery openings and workshops, containing images of him with Hillary Rodham Clinton, Jesse Jackson, and Spike Lee. There are also portraits of Powell from approximately 1975 to 2011, along with photographs of artists, writers, curators, and other notable individuals. There are also snapshots from Powell's extensive travels.
  - Professional (Box 49)
  - Powell Portraits (Box 49)
  - Portraits of Artists, Curators, Writers, etc. (Box 49)
  - Personal (Box 49)
- Works of Art, 1975-1995, 8 boxes
  The Works of Art Series includes works on paper (prints, drawings, and watercolor sketches) by Powell and other artists. Some of the works are dedicated to Powell.
  - Doug Huston (Box 51)
    "Tenure for Your Shoes" (1982)-Color Lithograph
  - Dana Chandler (Box 51)
    Includes offset lithographs: "White Amerika Chauvinist Male Fear Syndrom Series" (ca. 1970-71) and "Genocide Series" (ca. 1970-71)
  - Margaret Burroughs (Box 51)
    Includes offset lithographs: "In School Together" (1995), "Malcolm" (1995), "Jack Stones" (1995), "Mother and Child" (1995)
  - Amber Straight and John T. Smith (Box 52)
    Includes lithograph: Untitled (Bob Marley) (ca. 1980s) and woodcut print "Samella" (2004)
  - Mieke Smith and K. Hitchyst (sp?) (Box 52)
    Includes etching: "Lovers" (1997) and hand-colored etching: "Did You Eat Art Yet?" (1990)
  - Percy Martin and Aminah Brenda Lynn Robinson (Box 52)
    Includes etching: "Leopard with Ex-Friend Fire" (ca. 1980s) and etching with surface-rolled color: "Mud Vision" (1990)
  - Group Drawing, Aden Hachman, and John Wood (Box 52)
    Includes ink, colored markers: Group Drawing from Washington, DC (Howard University) (ca. 1977), linocut print: "Gemini" (Undated), and silkscreen: Print/Calling Card (ca. 1980)
  - Maria Garrido Saavedra, Claudia Widdis, and Neil Talbot (Box 52)
    Includes crayon: "Portrait of Richard J. Powell-Copenhagen, Denmark" (1984), etching/aquatint: "Puppet Reality" (1974), and embossed print: Untitled (1981)
  - Anonymous Norfolk State Univ. Student, Renee Leslie, and Aden Hachman (Box 52)
    Includes crayon/pencil Untitled (ca. 1978-79), mixed media: Untitled (ca. 1977), and color etching/aquatint: "Messiah" (1977)
  - E. Marion Parham, Unknown Artist, and Mieke Smith (Box 52)
    Includes etching: "Edict" (1980), Untitled hand-colored photograph mounted on board (ca. 1900), and etching/aquatint: "Fertility: The Sowing" (1997)
  - T. Khaliq, John T. Scott, and Kabuya Pam Bowens (Box 53)
    Includes etching: "Floating Mask I" (ca. 1980), ink on paper: "Tablet Head from I Remember Birmingham" (Nov. 30, 1999), and mixed media print: Untitled (ca. 1978)
  - Unknown Artist, Calvin Reid, and John T. Scott (Box 53)
    Includes lithograph: Untitled (Portfolio Exhibition Poster, School of the Art Institute of Chicago) (1981-82), etching/aquatint: "Chili House Bebop" (1977), and pencil on paper: "Study for the Sculpture Gateway for Beckworth" (May 11, 1988)
  - Smithsonian NMAA, Amaro Francisco, and Unknown Artist (Box 53)
    Includes: Smithsonian Print Portfolio: "Paintings of William H. Johnson," "O Sucesso Nao Acabou So Nos Falta Turismo" (Undated), and "Ori-Scent of Virtue" (Undated)
  - Exhibition Publicity and John W. Jones (Box 53)
    Includes: Chronicle of Higher Education Dec. 6, 1989 article on "The Blues Aesthetic" and "The State of Georgia" (Undated)
  - Powell Artwork (Box 53)
    Includes etching/working proof: "Remedial Ear Training" (1977), pencil on paper: "Two Self-Portraits, New Haven CT" (Nov. 21, 1982), and lithograph/watercolor: Untitled (Black Rock n' Roll) (1984)
  - Powell Artwork (Box 53)
    Includes pencil drawing: "Ying/Yang" (1977), watercolor: "Saint Anastasia" (2000), and watercolor: "Le Kufi/El Bari" (1980)
  - Richard J. Powell Artwork (Box 53)
    Includes collage: "Funky Broadway" (1978) and etching/first state: "Oracles" (1975)
  - Richard J. Powell Artwork (Box 53)
    Includes watercolor: Untitled (1979) and crayon: Untitled (1984)
  - Richard J. Powell Artwork (Box 53)
    Etching/aquatint: "Narrations: Tableau Vivant" Portrait of artist David Hammons, writer Debbie Wood, and RJP (1978-79)
  - Richard J. Powell Artwork (Box 53)
    Etching/aquatint: "Narrations: Eurydice in Hell" Powell and actress Marpessa Dawn in Lower Manhattan (1979)
  - Richard J. Powell Artwork (Box 54)
    Offset lithographs for Richard Wright Series: "Title Page for Richard Wright Series" (1977) and "Poem: Soulchant for Virgoman" (1977)
  - Richard J. Powell Artwork (Box 54)
    Photocopy: "Bon Voyage/Part Art Sale Invitation" (1984), photo-silkscreen: "Studies for Richard Wright Series" (1976), and ink on board: "Before/After" (1980)
  - Richard J. Powell Artwork (Box 54)
    "Richard Wright Series #2: The Long Dream" (1976), "Richard Wright Series #3: Subjugation of a Petty Bourgeois Degenerate" (1976), and "Petfood: Death of a Queen" (1981)
  - Richard J. Powell Artwork (Box 54)
    "Makeshift Ricky-Ayarn" (undated) and Untitled (undated)
  - Richard J. Powell Artwork (Box 54)
    "Richard Wright Series #4: Suspended over a Void" (1975) and "Richard Wright Series #10: The Man is Deranged, Life has Not Changed" (1977)
  - Richard J. Powell Artwork (Box 54)
    Ink on board: Untitled (1977) and ink/collage on board: "Lost in Music" (1979)
  - Richard J. Powell Artwork (Box 54)
    Ink on paper: Untitled (1983) and ink/collage on paper: "Drawing for Petfood Boogie" (1981)
  - Richard J. Powell Artwork (Box 54)
    Ink and pencil on paper: "Barry Series I" (1981) and "Barry Series II" (1981)
  - Richard J. Powell Artwork (Box 55)
    Ink and pencil on paper: "Barry Series III" (1981) and "Barry Series IV" (1981)
  - Richard J. Powell Artwork (Box 55)
    Watercolor on paper: "Question What Would you Buy If You had some Money?" (1983) and ink/collage on paper: "Self-Portrait as Tarzan" (1983)
  - Richard J. Powell Artwork (Box 55)
    Ink/collage on paper "Drawing for Petfood Revenge" (Undated)
  - Mieke Smith and Aden Hatchman (Box 55)
    Includes "My Country's Tears of Thee" (1996) and "Songe Vivant-For my mentor and cherished friend, Rick" (1982)
  - Photographs of Spartanburg, SC Train Wreck (Box 56)
    Four mounted 19th century photographs
  - Calvin Reid (Box 56)
    Untitled mounted photograph (1976) with dedication to Rick Powell on verso
  - Cynthia Haack and Aden Hachman (Box 56)
    Includes woodcut print: "Crab" (Undated), "Duke II" (1977), and "Black Girl IV" (1976)
  - Sam Shaw, Frank Stewart, and Rory Lawrence (Box 56)
    Includes b/w photograph: "Romare Bearden, Blackout, St. Martin" (ca. 1980), photography proof sheet: "Romare Bearden and Nude Model in Studio, Harlem NY" (ca. 1946), and pen/ink: Untitled (undated)
  - Aden Hachman, Jay Anderson, and DiLucco (Box 56)
    Includes color print: "Brother on the Block" (1977), photograph: "The African American Dance Ensemble" (undated), and ink/crayon on paper: Untitled (1985)
  - Johannes Larsen (Box 57)
    Untitled wood engraving (Head of a Rabbit) (undated, Early 20th c.)
  - Richard J. Powell and Others (Box 57)
    "Stone Souvenirs" lithograph series (1977)
  - Richard J. Powell and Others (Box 57)
    "Church Street" folios, etchings (1978)
  - Johannes Larsen (Box 57)
    Untitled woodcuts (Undated)
  - Aden Hachman (Box 57)
    "Brother on the Block" (1976)
  - Aden Hachman (Box 57)
    "Black Girl III" (1976)
  - Unknown Artist (Box 57)
    Untitled watercolor and pastel sketch (undated)
  - Janet ? (Box 57)
    Untitled collage and marker (undated)
  - Frank Stewart (Box 57)
    Photograph: "Romare Bearden" (ca. 1980)
  - Unknown Artist (Box 57)
    Untitled work on paper (Egyptian Scene) (undated)
  - Mark H. Montgomery (Box 57)
    "M.H.M." (undated)
  - Richard J. Powell Artwork (Box 57)
    Artist's Proof: "Jacob Lawrence" (1983)
  - Richard J. Powell Artwork (Box 57)
    Woodcut: "Rick Powell is Graduating…" (1975)
  - Aden Hachman, Barbara Woitawyzk (sp?), and I. Cotright (sp?) (Box 62)
    Includes aquatint: "Blues Series #2: The New Colorstruck Blues" (1978), Untitled Artist's Proof (1978), and color lithograph "Concrete Manual" (1981)
  - Richard J. Powell Artwork (Box 57)
    Woodcut on handmade paper: "Poodles: Fido" (1979)
  - Barbara Speight and Joseph Blanchard (Box 62)
    Includes Pencil Drawing of Richard J. Powell (1979) and Untitled Haiti (ca. 1960s)
  - Mark Pasquale, No Artist, and Nadya Brown (Box 62)
    Includes lithograph: "Hello Neighbor!" (1981), silkscreen: "Untitled (Signs) (Undated), and color etching/aquatint: "Beside the Lake Beneath the Trees" (1981)
  - Kabuya Pam Powens, Carol Law, and R. L. Martin (Box 62)
    Includes etching: "Genesis" (ca. 1977), silkscreen: "Bedtime Boogie" (1982), and lithograph "Zero Through Seven" (1981)
  - Richard J. Powell Artwork (Box 57)
    Crayon sketch: Untitled (1991)
  - Hester Simpson, Vincent Smith, and Conrad Gleber (Box 62)
    Includes lithograph: "Tender be Tough to Die" (1982), etching with surface-rolled color: Untitled (ca. 1980s), and lithograph: "Play it by Heart" (Undated)
  - Michael Miller and Mark H. Montgomery (Box 62)
    Includes etching/aquatint/soft-ground etching: Untitled (1981) and etching/aquatint: "Dressed Up: Betwixt and Between" (1976)
  - Richard J. Powell Artwork (Box 57)
  - Aden Hachman (Oversize-folder 2)
    Scope and Contents
    Blues Series #4: Tired of Being Lonely. Tired of Being Blue (1979)
- Audio, 1984-1999, 1 box
  The Audio Series contains cassette tapes of recorded conversations and interviews with artists such as Jacob Lawrence and Martin Puryear. The series also includes audio from events at the National Center for the Humanities and the Museum of Modern Art.
  The cassettes are organized by title and date when possible, although most are undated.
  - Museum of Modern Art: "Situation Critical? African-American Writers on African-American Artists: Tape 1," March 16, 1999 (Box 58)
  - Museum of Modern Art: "Situation Critical? African-American Writers on African-American Artists: Tape 2," March 16, 1999 (Box 58)
  - Fay Mitchell Henderson: "Black Culture and Modernism," March 22, 1990 (Box 58)
  - William H. Johnson: "Afro-American Music of the 1930s and 40s-Vol. 1," Undated (Box 58)
  - William H. Johnson: "Afro-American Music of the 1930s and 40s-Vol. 2," Undated (Box 58)
  - Soundings from the National Humanities Center: "Afro-American Culture, Literature, and Social Order-Parts 1-2," Undated (Box 58)
  - Soundings from the National Humanities Center: "Afro-American Culture, Literature, and Social Order -Parts 3-4," Undated (Box 58)
  - Soundings from the National Humanities Center: "Afro-American Culture, Literature, and Social Order -Parts 5-6," Undated (Box 58)
  - Soundings from the National Humanities Center, Michael Valdez Moses & Richard Powell, "Race and Representation," Undated (Box 58)
  - Soundings from the National Humanities Center: "Shakespeare's 'Green-ey'd Monster', and 'The Play's the Thing: Shakespeare Then and Now'," 1986 (Box 58)
  - Vivian Browne: "Funeral of Norman Lewis," Undated (Box 58)
  - Unknown: "Interview of Etherbert Halle (?)" (Box 58)
  - Unknown: "Jacob Lawrence Interview," June 20, 1984 (Box 58)
  - Unknown, "Jake Lawrence Lecture: 'Moten Swing,' 'I Will Move on up a Little Higher,' & 'Chains on Me," Undated (Box 58)
  - Unknown, "Martin Puryear-Tape 1" Meeting in Accord, NY, Undated (Box 58)